<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Posts on Nick Hauptvogel</title><link>https://www.hauptvogel.dev/posts/</link><description>Recent content in Posts on Nick Hauptvogel</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><copyright>&lt;a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">CC BY-NC 4.0&lt;/a></copyright><lastBuildDate>Sat, 19 Nov 2022 15:20:11 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://www.hauptvogel.dev/posts/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Copenhagen Student 101 - A guide to studying and surviving as a foreign student in Copenhagen, Denmark</title><link>https://www.hauptvogel.dev/posts/study_survive_in_copenhagen_guide/</link><pubDate>Sat, 19 Nov 2022 15:20:11 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://www.hauptvogel.dev/posts/study_survive_in_copenhagen_guide/</guid><description>Introduction In August 2022, I moved from my hometown Bremen in Germany to Copenhangen, Denmark, in order to start my Master&amp;rsquo;s Degree studies in Computer Science at the University of Copenhagen. After finishing my B.Sc. Degree in Computer Engineering in 2021, the strive for international experience and an continuation in the academic research environment led me to the decision to perform my Master&amp;rsquo;s degree abroad.
Early on, I started with the preparation of my stay abroad and gathered information about administrative tasks, but also student life advices.</description><content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="/static/copenhagen_guide.jpg" alt="A guide to survive in Copenhagen!"></p>
<h2 id="introduction">Introduction</h2>
<p>In August 2022, I moved from my hometown Bremen in Germany to Copenhangen,
Denmark, in order to start my Master&rsquo;s Degree studies in Computer Science at
the University of Copenhagen. After finishing my B.Sc. Degree in Computer
Engineering in 2021, the strive for international experience and an continuation
in the academic research environment led me to the decision to perform my
Master&rsquo;s degree abroad.</p>
<p>Early on, I started with the preparation of my stay abroad and gathered
information about administrative tasks, but also student life advices. For
that, I used several different sources, but soon found the information
landscape to be quite scarce. In order to facilitate the process of starting
the study life in Denmark for following students, I have decided to write a
(hopefully) comprehensive and complete guide to studying and surviving as a
foreign student in Copenhagen, Denmark.</p>
<p>Please bear in mind that many of the described processes only apply to EU
citizens (and some also relate to the University of Copenhagen) and might be
different for Non-EU students or other universities. Also, processes might
change in the future, in which case they can deviate from the following
descriptions. But enough of the disclaimer, let us start with the guide!</p>
<h2 id="before-moving-to-denmark">Before Moving to Denmark</h2>
<h3 id="residence-permit---online-preparation">Residence Permit - Online Preparation</h3>
<p>There are a couple of (mostly administrative) tasks that you can initiate before
moving to Denmark. First and foremost, the residence permit application process
can be started before moving to the country. For that, the University of
Copenhagen sends an invitation containing a link to the application portal.
After receiving the e-mail and clicking on the link, follow the instructions in
the application process and fill out the so-called &ldquo;OD1&rdquo; form online.</p>
<p>In the process, there are different documents that need to be uploaded. The
Declaration of Self-Support is not required to be signed beforehand, so you can
just download and upload the same document again. Second, the Declaration of
study activity is superfluous if you have already received your admission
letter from the university. In that case, just upload the letter of admission
instead. Third, the sworn declaration needs to be downloaded, signed (also
digitally) and then re-uploaded.</p>
<p>It is possible for the residence permit to apply without already having an address
in Denmark. In that case, just insert your home address, your Danish address will be
then requested once you have arrived.</p>
<p>At the end of the process, you have to book an appointment at SIRI (Styrelsen
for International Rekruttering og Integration) to finish the process. For that,
it is important to book the appointment via the link in the e-mail, <strong>not</strong>
via the link at the end of the OD1 form fill out! When choosing the link from
the mail, it is possible to choose a special opening day of the administration
office only for students, on which you receive the residence permit on the same
day. After having booked the appointment, note down the booking number. It is
the number you have to enter at the entrance of the administration office.</p>
<h3 id="cpr-civil-registration-number---online-preparation">CPR Civil Registration Number - Online Preparation</h3>
<p>The civil registration number is the core of your administrative life in Denmark.
It is needed to access government services online, open a bank account, access
health insurance, have a student job etc. Unlike common belief, the CPR
application can also be started before receiving the residence permit (at least
for EU students). However, for the CPR, a housing contract and an official
address in Denmark is needed.</p>
<p>To apply for the CPR online, go to the website of the
<a href="https://ihcph.kk.dk/cpr-registration-0">International House Copenhagen</a>. From
here, you can start the application process.</p>
<h3 id="find-housing">Find Housing</h3>
<p>One of the most difficult tasks, especially when you have not yet arrived in Denmark,
is to find housing. Many alternatives offer in-person viewings, which is not feasible
beforehand. And, if you are like me, you do not want to move to a country without
knowing where to stay the first night!
<strong>TODO</strong></p>
<h3 id="find-a-student-job">Find a Student Job</h3>
<p><strong>TODO</strong></p>
<h2 id="after-moving-to-denmark">After moving to Denmark</h2>
<h3 id="residence-permit---in-person-appointment">Residence Permit - In-Person Appointment</h3>
<p>One of the first things you can do after arriving in Denmark is attending the appointment
at SIRI, which you booked during the online preparation. The Copenhagen office is located
in Carl Jacobsens Vej 39, 2500 Valby. Be there in time before your appointment and enter
your booking confirmation code at the entrance (which is on the main street, not in the
back courtyard). You need your passport / national ID in original form at the appointment.</p>
<p>Furthermore, remember to bring the following documents in printed form:</p>
<ul>
<li>OD1 Application</li>
<li>Color Copy of National ID</li>
<li>Passport Photo Original</li>
<li>Declaration for Self-Support</li>
<li>Letter of Admission</li>
<li>Sworn Declaration of OD1 form</li>
</ul>
<p>Even though those documents are stated to be strictly required, in many cases you don&rsquo;t need
to show them (given that you uploaded the relevant ones beforehand, of course).</p>
<h3 id="cpr-civil-registration-number---book-appointment">CPR Civil Registration Number - Book Appointment</h3>
<p>Approximately two weeks after the CPR online application, you receive an e-mail with the
request to book an in-person appointment for the CPR number. Choose a date that suits you best.</p>
<h3 id="cpr-civil-registration-number---in-person-appointment">CPR Civil Registration Number - In-Person Appointment</h3>
<p>When the day of the CPR appointment has come, you go to the International House in Copenhagen,
which is located on Nyropsgade 1, 1602 K칮benhavn V. For this, you are asked to bring your
housing contract and the residence permit, which you received at SIRI before. After showing
the documents, you have the chance to request the NemID (which you should absolutely do). Next
to your CPR number, you then receive a letter for the activation of the NemID. This is not needed
until the so-called code card arrives via mail approx. a week later.</p>
<h3 id="nemid">NemID</h3>
<p>I have seen many different explanations of the NemID, which all seemt a bit abstract to me, so I
will try to explain it myself as simple as possible. In order to log in to government or other
official online services, an authentication is used which is called NemID. It is tightly coupled to
the CPR number and involves a 2-Factor-Authentification with your phone or a physical code card
(I would highly recommend the app, though).</p>
<p>In order to activate NemID, wait for the letter sent to you after the CPR appointment containing
the code card. When it has arrived, you use the code card and the letter from the CPR appointment
and follow the instructions. In the process, you set a password, which you can use to log in to
the NemID app. Now, everytime you need to log on to an official online service, where you can use
NemID, you enter your CPR number, the password, and confirm the log in in the NemID app.</p>
<p>NB: NemID is replaced by a new system called MitID. To activate the MitID, simply download the app
and follow the instructions. Many online services now exclusively offer the authentication via MitID.</p>
<h3 id="bank-account">Bank Account</h3>
<p>Before you can open a Danish bank account, an account with a cheap conversion of currencies saves
you a lot of conversion fees. For that, I use Revolut (so do many other fellow students), which
makes it easy and cheap to transfer money (e.g. in EUR) and swap it to DKK (with a maximum of
0.5% fee after a certain money volume).</p>
<p>If you want to receive government support like SU or Boligst칮tte, however, a Danish bank account facilitates the procress immensely. After hearing about long queues and waiting times for banks like
Danske Bank, the de-facto standard for many students, I tried the Danish online bank Lunar, which lets
you open an account online without any waiting time. The approval process needed approximately one week,
and afterwards you are set to go. The Danish government transfers money to your so-called NemKonto,
which can be seen as the government-known account. You can request your account at Lunar to be your
NemKonto directly from the app.</p>
<h3 id="digital-post">Digital Post</h3>
<p>Another fully digitalised system is the so-called Digital Post, which almost completely replaces the physical letter correspondence with the authorities. It is a special E-Mail inbox, which is used to
communicate with different institutions in the Danish administrative. There is an app (called Digital Post) you can use, otherwise you find your inbox on all of the following websites:</p>
<ul>
<li>borger.dk</li>
<li>e-Boks.dk</li>
<li>mit.dk</li>
</ul>
<p>NB: You can see mail from authorities on all of the websites. However, certain banks or companies can
have agreements with only one of those providers, making their mails only visible in the corresponding provider&rsquo;s inbox. One example could be payslips, which could be issued by a company e.g. only in e-Boks. Therefore, it can be beneficial to check all of the providers regularly.</p>
<h3 id="mobilepay">MobilePay</h3>
<h3 id="tax-card">Tax Card</h3>
<h3 id="public-transport">Public Transport</h3>
<h3 id="boligst칮tte">Boligst칮tte</h3>
<h2 id="working--su">Working &amp; SU</h2>
]]></content></item><item><title>Hello World</title><link>https://www.hauptvogel.dev/posts/hello-world/</link><pubDate>Wed, 24 Aug 2022 22:20:11 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://www.hauptvogel.dev/posts/hello-world/</guid><description>Hej! Jeg hedder Nick og jeg er 23 친r gammel. Jeg er fra Tyskland og skal studere datalogi p친 K칮benhavns Universitet fra september 2022. Jeg er flyttet til K칮benhavn for et par dage siden, men jeg har l칝rt dansk i et par m친neder. Med indl칝g som disse vil jeg gerne dokumentere mine fremskridt med at l칝re sproget.
More than that, I want to utilize this blog to keep track of my studies&amp;rsquo; progress.</description><content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="/static/copenhagen_helloworld.jpg" alt="Hello Copenhagen!"></p>
<p>Hej! Jeg hedder Nick og jeg er 23 친r gammel. Jeg er fra Tyskland og skal studere datalogi p친 K칮benhavns Universitet fra september 2022.
Jeg er flyttet til K칮benhavn for et par dage siden, men jeg har l칝rt dansk i et par m친neder. Med indl칝g som disse vil jeg gerne dokumentere mine fremskridt med at l칝re sproget.</p>
<p>More than that, I want to utilize this blog to keep track of my studies&rsquo; progress. From time to time, I will compose short articles, either about the Danish language, a particularly interesting topic from my M.Sc. studies or just a random thought that came to my mind while biking to the university. 游</p>
<p>Welcome to my blog and stay tuned! 游닀</p>
]]></content></item></channel></rss>