<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Posts on Nick Hauptvogel</title><link>https://www.hauptvogel.dev/posts/</link><description>Recent content in Posts on Nick Hauptvogel</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><copyright>&lt;a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">CC BY-NC 4.0&lt;/a></copyright><lastBuildDate>Sun, 06 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0100</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://www.hauptvogel.dev/posts/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>My 2nd Season in Triathlon - Shifting the Focus</title><link>https://www.hauptvogel.dev/posts/triathlon_lessons_learnt_2/</link><pubDate>Sun, 06 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://www.hauptvogel.dev/posts/triathlon_lessons_learnt_2/</guid><description>My previous post about the first year in the sport of triathlon mostly covered essential and basic insights, how to start and what to expect. After my second year, it is time to shift the focus from beginner to intermediate and talk about some different experiences that have resonated with me during this year. While still being relatively new to the sport, I am trying to learn and implement more and more nuances into my own training and racing, bit by bit.</description><content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="/static/tri_2/triathlon_ll_2.jpg" alt="Karlstrup Kalkgrav - The same race location!"></p>
<p>My previous post about the first year in the sport of triathlon mostly covered essential and basic insights, how to start and what to expect. After my second year, it is time to shift the focus from beginner to intermediate and talk about some different experiences that have resonated with me during this year. While still being relatively new to the sport, I am trying to learn and implement more and more nuances into my own training and racing, bit by bit.</p>
<p>As a short recap: I’ve participated in four triathlon races this year, including one sprint, two Olympic and one middle distance (70.3), thereby completing my first half Iron Man and getting to know the Olympic distance a little better. At the same time, I achieved my first age group win (with small age groups) at the sprint race. On top of these, the Copenhagen half marathon and 2km open water swim around Christiansborg castle were checked off the list in 2024.</p>
<h2 id="the-swim">The swim</h2>
<p>Much of my first post described the obstacle of learning how to swim at all (in front crawl technique) when getting into the sport. Fast forward two years, and I was consistently among the first 10-15% of swimmers in my races this year. On top of that, at the open water swim event in Copenhagen, I could finish in the top 11% of all participants. If someone showed me those results two years ago, I would not have believed that swimming would actually not be my weak point in a race, but set me up fairly far in front, where I would often keep my position on the bike, only to lose a lot of ground on the run.</p>
<p>The main ingredients for this improvement in the water, in my opinion, are consistency and coaching. I talked about consistency before, to get comfortable in the beginning. After making the initial steps though, it is equally important to keep on swimming, at least twice a week. Those sessions do not necessarily have to be long nor straining, but should aim at reminding the body how the swimming position feels like, more than once a week.</p>
<p>Second is proper coaching including feedback. Swimming is such a technical discipline that it does not make any sense to circle around in a pool on your own without any input on form, especially after the initial “getting comfortable”. I was lucky to focus a lot on swimming in my exchange semester in Toronto, where I spent three times a week in the university pool with the local triathlon club. My advice is therefore to swim in a club or with a coach, whenever possible.</p>
<p>In terms of what to focus on technique-wise (and in which order), I picked up the mnemonic PDLC from Joe Friel’s “Triathlete’s Training Bible”:</p>
<ul>
<li>Posture: Long and straight body, chin tucked in, eyesight to the bottom of the pool (slightly in front) and head rotating in line with the spinal axis to breathe.</li>
<li>Direction: Arms extend in line with shoulder after entering the water, no crossing over the centerline</li>
<li>Length: Long extension of the arm in front, trying to improve distance per stroke</li>
<li>Catch: High elbow catch, diamond shape of the angle between the upper and lower arm</li>
</ul>
<p>In his book, Joe advises to focus on and achieve proper technique in one stage before moving on to the next. Another advice, which I picked up from several different places, would be to start with short “intervals”, e.g. 50m, without major effort, explicitly focusing on the technique. In longer intervals, you should make sure to keep proper form until the end of the effort, and otherwise keep it shorter (or lower the interval intensity in favor of the technique).</p>
<p><strong>What I want to improve and work on over the winter and until next season?</strong></p>
<p>I would love to work with a camera underwater to get visual feedback myself. Moreover, my plan is to get technically stronger in pool-swimming specialties, such as flip turns and dolphin kicks.</p>
<h2 id="the-bike">The bike</h2>
<p>Moving on to the bike, there is not a lot of advice I can give regarding technique or improvements in power. The only real advice that I followed myself at the beginning of the year, is to get a professional bike fit before increasing the bike volume, as it can prevent injuries, increase power, comfort and optimize the aero position at the same time. A bike fit often includes adjusting the shoes, saddle height, angle and setback, as well as the aerobars’ positions.</p>
<p>For me, biking is the discipline where it comes down to the variety of sessions (including long aerobic rides and short high-intensity intervals) and duration on the bike that determine your progress. The following power curves (Maximal power in Watts vs. duration) compare the first month with a power meter (February) with the last month (September). It is to note that there are a lot of variables, like different power meters, different focus in sessions etc. that cloud the comparison.  I still think that the overall trend is visible well enough. I improved my FTP to 4.1W/kg, which is considered as a Cat. 3 rider.</p>
<p><img src="/static/tri_2/powercurve.png" alt="Power Curve"></p>
<p><strong>What I want to improve and work on over the winter and until next season?</strong></p>
<p>I would like to include more technique-related sessions in my training, for example high and low cadence work, sprinting, big gear accelerations. Otherwise, I would like to improve more on the translation of power to speed, mainly influenced by aerodynamic drag, by investing in some new equipment for the time-trial bike and working on my aero position.</p>
<h1 id="the-run">The run</h1>
<p>As mentioned before, my relation to running is the most difficult of the three disciplines. After a pleasing half marathon in Canada in October 2023, I woke up with a sharp pain in my right knee two weeks later. Taking a break for more than 8 weeks and getting a MRI, as well as an X-ray, did not bring up more than “overuse” as an explanation. That is also why I started 2024 with zero weekly kilometers.</p>
<p>What did I learn from this? Sometimes, you cannot change what happens when stressing your body with training. It is hard to accept, but it does not make any sense to force an injury to persist or re-appear when starting too quickly again. Instead, I tried to focus on strength work for the legs (more on that later) and gradually increased my volume week after week, as apparent from the following chart.</p>
<p><img src="/static/tri_2/runweekly.png" alt="Weekly volume running"></p>
<p>The only weeks with strong outliers were race weeks like the middle distance (16/06) and half marathon (15/09). However, the overall trend shows a slight increase each week, such that I am back to 20-30km per week, pain-free. Also, I was able to come close to a big milestone, that is sub 20min 5k with 20:06 and a new half marathon best with 1:36:02, four minutes faster than in Toronto 2023.</p>
<p><strong>What I want to improve and work on over the winter and until next season?</strong></p>
<p>Running is arguably my weakest discipline, so the plan is to increase speed with a big VO2Max block over the winter. I signed up for a winter running series with five 10k races to monitor my progress. Simultaneously, I want to work on and improve my leg strength, as well as responsiveness with plyometric exercises. The next big goals are sub 20min 5k and sub 40min 10k.</p>
<h1 id="strength-and-mobility">Strength and mobility</h1>
<ol>
<li>Strength training, mobility (dynamic), static stretching</li>
</ol>
<p>Coming from a gym background, the value of strength and resistance training was already known to me before starting triathlon seriously. However, due to the timely investment of the three disciplines, strength training lost a lot of its importance to me. After experiencing the running injury and reminding myself of the cruciality, strength training started to be part of my weekly routine again. To keep the sessions short and productive, I focus on full-body compound exercises to create stimuli across all muscle regions. This includes, deadlifts, squats, military press, bench press, pull-ups, barbell rows and single leg stability exercises.</p>
<p><strong>What I want to improve and work on over the winter and until next season?</strong></p>
<p>During the winter, I want to increase the gym volume from one to two sessions per week to build more strength and support my joints, bones and tendons with the stress from endurance training.</p>
<h1 id="money">Money</h1>
<p>Triathlon is not particularly known for being a cheap sport. Especially the bike equipment accounts for a major share in the beginning. I would therefore like to list some of the ways to save money (after the initial shopping spree).</p>
<ul>
<li>Carb Drinks / Gels: Due to their constant requirement, carb drinks and gels can be seen as a major part of the monthly costs. After experimenting and reading around and into the science of glucose/fructose ratios, different types of carbohydrates etc., I can recommend the following website that lists a variety of DIY carb drink solutions instead of buying pre-made mixes: <a href="https://www.climbingnutrition.com/supplements/make-your-own-sports-drink/">https://www.climbingnutrition.com/supplements/make-your-own-sports-drink/</a>. Taken from the website, I settled on a mixture of maltodextrin and plain sugar 1:1, with some salt and optional lemon juice for flavoring.</li>
<li>Bike equipment: Blessing and curse about the bike is that there always is something new and shiny to buy. Being in a club and getting to see the other’s gear at the weekly long ride or the club-internal time-trial contributes to that feeling. However, after the initial investment of a time-trial bike (which is already an advantage to a normal road bike), it can save you money to put the blinders on and focus on your aero position and strength on the bike instead to produce the speed. I am now setting aside a certain monthly amount as a saving to rejoice the process of buying a new bike, only when the money is actually available and intended for this purpose.</li>
<li>Club wear: A way to save money in a club is to listen around and see whether an older member wants to weed out some club wear (often to make some space for the new wear!). This way, you get shirts and bib pants, branded, with little or no payment.</li>
<li>Early race entries: Most races announce their next season’s date at the end of the previous season, along with early bird discounts. This is a good time to plan and book your races for the next season, such that you don’t pay the most expensive fee two weeks before the race.</li>
</ul>
<h1 id="planning">Planning</h1>
<p>After spending my first year trying to figure out by myself how to train in the best way, I started working with a coach at the beginning of 2024. I can say now that, at least for me, this is one of the wisest investments to make. Not only is it nice to have someone look over your training and make a plan, it is especially useful if you tend to overthink and obsess with details. In this case, it feels good to trust a coach and “just” execute, instead of worrying about over- or undertraining. Additionally, it is useful to have an external stakeholder, giving you the subtle pressure to not skip a session just because you do not feel like it. Since February, I was therefore able to keep training consistently, as shown here by weekly training stress score (TSS).</p>
<p><img src="/static/tri_2/consistency.png" alt="Weekly volume overall"></p>
<p><strong>What I want to improve and work on over the winter and until next season?</strong></p>
<p>I am still at the start of this chapter, but looking forward to planning the next season with my coach. I would love to be involved in topics like periodization and prioritization of races to fine-grain the annual training plan.</p>
<h1 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h1>
<p>While already addressed in each section, I have a couple of goals for the winter and next season, that I want to list explicitly</p>
<ul>
<li>Technique work in the pool and on the bike</li>
<li>Strength and speed for the run</li>
<li>Sub 20min 5k and Sub 40min 10k</li>
<li>Plan the next season: I would like to race my first proper 70.3 (this year, the swim was cancelled due to bacterial pollution) and another middle / some more Olympic/sprint distances. Longer distances will be saved up until a later point (2026?).</li>
</ul>
]]></content></item><item><title>One Year of Triathlon - Lessons Learnt</title><link>https://www.hauptvogel.dev/posts/triathlon_lessons_learnt/</link><pubDate>Fri, 01 Sep 2023 12:20:11 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://www.hauptvogel.dev/posts/triathlon_lessons_learnt/</guid><description>Introduction In 2022, while watching a local triathlon event in my hometown of Bremen, I reminisced about the time when I participated in athletics during my school years. The feeling of excitement and butterflies before a race, the competitive atmosphere, and observing all the athletes being prepared resonated with me once more after several years without engaging in competitive sports. Shortly thereafter, I relocated to Copenhagen to pursue my Master&amp;rsquo;s degree and discovered a new community within the local triathlon club, TRI4.</description><content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="/static/triathlon_ll.jpg" alt="Karlstrup Kalkgrav - The second race location!"></p>
<h2 id="introduction">Introduction</h2>
<p>In 2022, while watching a local triathlon event in my hometown of Bremen, I reminisced about the time when I participated in athletics during my school years. The feeling of excitement and butterflies before a race, the competitive atmosphere, and observing all the athletes being prepared resonated with me once more after several years without engaging in competitive sports. Shortly thereafter, I relocated to Copenhagen to pursue my Master&rsquo;s degree and discovered a new community within the local triathlon club, TRI4. I commenced training and competing once again, and in my inaugural season in 2023, I successfully completed four races. This article serves as a brief recap of my first year in triathlon, highlighting the lessons I&rsquo;ve learned so far, as well as outlining my future plans in the sport.</p>
<h2 id="lessons-learnt">Lessons learnt</h2>
<h3 id="sporttraining">Sport/Training</h3>
<ol>
<li>
<h4 id="learning-a-new-discipline">Learning a New Discipline</h4>
</li>
</ol>
<p>The biggest and most obvious thing I learned is a whole new discipline. I knew how to run and how to bike on a race bike (at least technically), but my swimming abilities were limited to breaststroke and simply staying afloat in the water. I had never swum for speed or time, nor had I ever used the freestyle technique. So, as I began my training in the club, you can imagine how the initial swimming sessions went. I could barely crawl one lane (i.e., 50m) in the pool, and it&rsquo;s safe to say there was no recognizable technique involved at all.</p>
<p>I did what most beginner swimmers tend to do: I stressed myself out about &ldquo;never learning it at all&rdquo; and &ldquo;not being a swimmer type,&rdquo; among other things. Of course, I also watched countless online tutorials on how to start swimming and improve my technique. However, I discovered that the best way to start was simply to train consistently, no matter how bad it felt at first. Those initial sessions were exhausting; I couldn&rsquo;t even focus on the exercises because I struggled to breathe properly for just one lane. But after a few weeks, I had a breakthrough moment during one of my swim sessions. After starting the swim session as usual, I suddenly felt a certain relaxation in the water, more than ever before. I noticed myself exhaling slowly underwater through my nose, something I couldn&rsquo;t do before. I hadn&rsquo;t actively trained for this; my body had simply adapted to the environment and relaxed. From that point on, I was able to actively participate in exercises, swim 200m consecutively, and more.</p>
<p>Now, I&rsquo;m at a point where I still feel like a complete beginner in terms of my technique, but I&rsquo;m confident that I can maintain a moderate heart rate and breathing pattern for a considerable time in the water. My races have included swims ranging from 500m to 1500m, and during the last two, I managed to swim without taking any breaks. I plan to continue training to improve my technique, but I&rsquo;m very pleased to have acquired this new skill.</p>
<ol start="2">
<li>
<h4 id="overcoming-fear-of-open-water-swimming">Overcoming Fear of Open Water Swimming</h4>
</li>
</ol>
<p>Starting my journey in January, the first few months of swimming sessions were exclusively indoors. Even my first race in May was held in a pool. Naturally, I was excited for my first open water swim training. However, after trying it out for the first time by myself in a nearby lake, I felt similar to my first indoor swimming experiences. I couldn&rsquo;t swim more than 25m without stopping and had to switch to breaststroke. The inability to see the ground and the sensation of being alone in the water made me extremely uncomfortable, a feeling I even experienced when swimming breaststroke.</p>
<p>With this experience in mind, I attended my first club training session, which turned out to be different from what I had expected. The combination of clear water and people around me gave me the relaxation I needed to apply the techniques I had learned in open water. While I&rsquo;m still not 100% confident in open water, especially when I&rsquo;m alone or in the open ocean, I am grateful for facing this fear and taking the first steps to overcome it.</p>
<ol start="3">
<li>
<h4 id="expect-to-be-mediocre">Expect to be Mediocre</h4>
</li>
</ol>
<p>Being a competitive person, I always tend to compare myself to others, especially when it is so easy and objective to compare timed races. However, coming into a new sport, I knew I had to expect to be mediocre at best. Even with my limited running background, people who have trained in all disciplines for years have a significant advantage and will (of course!) perform better. It would be disappointing if that were not the case! Therefore, having realistic expectations is key here. Even though I like to be at the front, I willingly accepted that I would be in the middle of the pack and decided to have fun with it, for example, by trying to keep up with the faster runners and pushing myself even further.</p>
<ol start="4">
<li>
<h4 id="discpline-and-motivation">Discpline and Motivation</h4>
</li>
</ol>
<p>Most of the time, training is super fun. But there will be days where you just don&rsquo;t feel like it. When it is the second workout of the day. When it is raining. When it is cold. When you have had a long day the day before. Or all of it together. I won&rsquo;t preach to always go for a session, regardless of how you feel. If you feel strained and have had some hard workouts in the days before, it might be wise to use this opportunity to rest. But if you are well-rested and the only thing holding you back is your mind, then you should actively decide to overcome this mindset and go for it. In 98% of the cases, you will feel better and more accomplished afterwards. In the remaining 2%, you can take it easy the next day. The feeling of overcoming your mind is worth it in 100% of the cases.</p>
<ol start="5">
<li>
<h4 id="nutrition-is-its-own-discipline">Nutrition is its Own Discipline</h4>
</li>
</ol>
<p>Next to the technical abilities in all three disciplines, there is a cross-disciplinary ability that has to be trained as well: Nutrition. General advice tends to be around 60g of carbohydrates per hour, but it varies with body weight, gender, and the distance of the race. In shorter races (like sprints), nutrition plays only a minor role; the longer the race, however, the more important it becomes. In order to avoid trying to fuel with 60g of carbs per hour (in a 4-hour race, this amounts to 240g of carbohydrates, which is roughly equivalent to a quarter kilogram of sugar) on race day, you need to train your nutrition as well. This is an aspect in which I am not very experienced yet, but I am excited to train and learn more about it, especially for longer distances. Of course, nutrition around the workouts is at least equally important, but I will not go into detail here, as it could fill another blog post.</p>
<h3 id="social">Social</h3>
<ol>
<li>
<h4 id="club-culture">Club Culture</h4>
</li>
</ol>
<p>With their own word for it (foreningskultur, i.e., club culture), it is understandable that clubs of various sorts enjoy great popularity in Denmark. Throughout the year, I have met a diverse group of people, many of whom I have become friends with. Sharing sports as a common interest is a strong bond, and triathletes also tend to be highly ambitious and motivating individuals. It is a wonderful feeling to be motivated towards better performance in training and competitions, while also representing a club together.</p>
<ol start="2">
<li>
<h4 id="danish-language">Danish Language</h4>
</li>
</ol>
<p>After having started my studies in August 2022, I joined the club in an intro course around 4 weeks after moving to Denmark. Obviously, I was not as proficient in Danish to understand what native speakers talked about, and my skills were limited to basic conversations. As almost all members of the club are Danes, I was suddenly surrounded by strangers speaking a mostly unknown language, not an easy situation to start with. However, after introducing myself as a German, they all switched to English (some even to German) to start a conversation with me, even to explain the workouts. As I gained more experience with the language, I slowly started to keep up more, no longer needed separate English instructions, and now use the social time on bike rides or slow runs to improve my Danish-speaking abilities.</p>
<ol start="3">
<li>
<h4 id="danish-culture">Danish Culture</h4>
</li>
</ol>
<p>Lastly, I want to emphasize some core values that I had the pleasure to experience while being in the club: trust and respect. Even though triathlon is an individual sport on race day, training still feels like a team effort. Everyone is respected, regardless of their skill level, and coaches are respectful and extremely supportive. This is something I had not experienced in other sports before, and it is a nice feeling to be part of such a community.</p>
<h2 id="future-plans">Future Plans</h2>
<p>To conclude my summary, I want to talk briefly about my plans after winter. I am currently on exchange at the University of Toronto and joined the local triathlon club; excited to start training until end of the year (without any competitions). I hope to continue training next spring in Copenhagen and compete in a variety of races again. For now, the plan is to stick to similar distances as this year (and hopefully improve), but you never know what the future holds. I am very grateful to be a part of this community and look forward to the next season!</p>
]]></content></item><item><title>Copenhagen Student 101 - A guide to studying and surviving as a foreign student in Copenhagen, Denmark</title><link>https://www.hauptvogel.dev/posts/study_survive_in_copenhagen_guide/</link><pubDate>Sat, 19 Nov 2022 15:20:11 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://www.hauptvogel.dev/posts/study_survive_in_copenhagen_guide/</guid><description>Introduction In August 2022, I moved from my hometown Bremen in Germany to Copenhangen, Denmark, in order to start my Master&amp;rsquo;s Degree studies in Computer Science at the University of Copenhagen, after finishing my B.Sc. Degree in Computer Engineering in 2021.
Early on, I started with the preparation of my stay abroad and gathered information about administrative tasks, but also student life advices. For that, I used several different sources, but soon found the information landscape to be quite scarce.</description><content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="/static/copenhagen_guide.jpg" alt="A guide to survive in Copenhagen!"></p>
<h2 id="introduction">Introduction</h2>
<p>In August 2022, I moved from my hometown Bremen in Germany to Copenhangen,
Denmark, in order to start my Master&rsquo;s Degree studies in Computer Science at
the University of Copenhagen, after finishing my B.Sc. Degree in Computer
Engineering in 2021.</p>
<p>Early on, I started with the preparation of my stay abroad and gathered
information about administrative tasks, but also student life advices. For
that, I used several different sources, but soon found the information
landscape to be quite scarce. In order to facilitate the process of starting
the study life in Denmark for following students, I have decided to write a
(hopefully) comprehensive guide to studying and surviving as a
foreign student in Copenhagen, Denmark.</p>
<p>Most of the information I provide are complementary explanations or hints for obstacles I stumbled upon during my first weeks in Denmark. Please bear in mind that many of the described processes may only apply to EU
citizens (and some also relate to the University of Copenhagen) and might be
different for Non-EU students or other universities. Also, processes might
change in the future, in which case they can deviate from the following
descriptions. But enough of the disclaimer, let us start with the guide!</p>
<h2 id="before-moving-to-denmark">Before Moving to Denmark</h2>
<h3 id="residence-permit---online-preparation">Residence Permit - Online Preparation</h3>
<p>There are a couple of (mostly administrative) tasks that you can initiate before
moving to Denmark. First and foremost, the residence permit application process
can be started before moving to the country. For that, the University of
Copenhagen sends an invitation containing a link to the application portal.
After receiving the e-mail and clicking on the link, follow the instructions in
the application process and fill out the so-called &ldquo;OD1&rdquo; form online.</p>
<p>In the process, there are different documents that need to be uploaded. The
Declaration of Self-Support is not required to be signed beforehand, so you can
just download and upload the same document again. Second, the Declaration of
study activity is superfluous if you have already received your admission
letter from the university. In that case, just upload the letter of admission
instead. Third, the sworn declaration needs to be downloaded, signed (also
digitally) and then re-uploaded.</p>
<p>It is possible for the residence permit to apply without already having an address
in Denmark. In that case, just insert your home address, your Danish address will be
then requested once you have arrived.</p>
<p>At the end of the process, you have to book an appointment at SIRI (Styrelsen
for International Rekruttering og Integration) to finish the process. For that,
it is important to book the appointment via the link in the e-mail, <strong>not</strong>
via the link at the end of the OD1 form fill out! When choosing the link from
the mail, it is possible to choose a special opening day of the administration
office only for students, on which you receive the residence permit on the same
day. After having booked the appointment, note down the booking number. It is
the number you have to enter at the entrance of the administration office.</p>
<h3 id="cpr-civil-registration-number---online-preparation">CPR Civil Registration Number - Online Preparation</h3>
<p>The civil registration number is the core of your administrative life in Denmark.
It is needed to access government services online, open a bank account, access
health insurance, have a student job etc. Unlike common belief, the CPR
application can also be started before receiving the residence permit (at least
for EU students). However, for the CPR, a housing contract and an official
address in Denmark is needed.</p>
<p>To apply for the CPR online, go to the website of the
<a href="https://ihcph.kk.dk/cpr-registration-0">International House Copenhagen</a>. From
here, you can start the application process.</p>
<h3 id="find-housing">Find Housing</h3>
<p>One of the most difficult tasks, especially when you have not yet arrived in Denmark,
is to find housing. Many alternatives offer in-person viewings, which is not feasible
beforehand. And, if you are like me, you do not want to move to a country without
knowing where to stay the first night!</p>
<p>There is no definitive answer on finding the right housing and this topic could fill entire articles on its own. The only thing I want to mention here is my experience: Firstly, there are dorms with a waiting list system, mainly administrated by two vendors: kollegierneskontor.dk (KKIK) and s.dk. You can sign up for accommodations and will receive an offer once you are on top of the wait list, but generally, you never know when this will happen. Not great for a fixed start of studies. Nonetheless, the accommodations are usually cheaper than some other options.</p>
<p>Another option are dorms without a wait list. The one I found with spots available is The MARK (themark.dk), a lovely dorm with big common areas and a welcoming community a bit outside of the central city (but well connected by train). For more dorm possibilities, it makes most sense to search for lists and collections of current available dorms online.</p>
<h3 id="find-a-student-job">Find a Student Job</h3>
<p>Similar to the housing matter, a guide to finding a student job could fill articles on its own, which is why I&rsquo;ll focus on my experience. There are multiple portals listing student jobs online (e.g. LinkedIn, Glassdoor, Indeed etc.), on which you can find different available student jobs. Mostly, there are application portals that list all required documentation (e.g. CV, transcripts) etc., make sure to provide everything that is required by the employer. And a tip from me: If a cover letter is optional, just go for it! It&rsquo;ll make a difference.</p>
<p>After an online application, an interview is often the next step to getting a student job. Make sure to align a potential interview date with your availability in-person, otherwise you could ask for a virtual interview instead. However, again a tip from me: Go for the in-person interview. It is just easier to connect with people that way.</p>
<h2 id="after-moving-to-denmark">After moving to Denmark</h2>
<h3 id="residence-permit---in-person-appointment">Residence Permit - In-Person Appointment</h3>
<p>One of the first things you can do after arriving in Denmark is attending the appointment
at SIRI, which you booked during the online preparation. Be there in time before your appointment and enter
your booking confirmation code at the entrance. You need your passport / national ID in original form at the appointment.</p>
<p>Furthermore, remember to bring the following documents in printed form:</p>
<ul>
<li>OD1 Application</li>
<li>Color Copy of National ID</li>
<li>Passport Photo Original</li>
<li>Declaration for Self-Support</li>
<li>Letter of Admission</li>
<li>Sworn Declaration of OD1 form</li>
</ul>
<p>Even though those documents are stated to be strictly required, in many cases you don&rsquo;t need
to show them (given that you uploaded them beforehand, of course).</p>
<h3 id="cpr-civil-registration-number---book-appointment">CPR Civil Registration Number - Book Appointment</h3>
<p>Approximately two weeks after the CPR online application, you receive an e-mail with the
request to book an in-person appointment for the CPR number. Choose a date that suits you best.</p>
<h3 id="cpr-civil-registration-number---in-person-appointment">CPR Civil Registration Number - In-Person Appointment</h3>
<p>When the day of the CPR appointment has come, you go to the International House. For this, you are asked to bring your
housing contract and the residence permit, which you received at SIRI before. After showing
the documents, you have the chance to request the NemID (which you should absolutely do). Next
to your CPR number, you then receive a letter for the activation of the NemID. This is not needed
until the so-called code card arrives via mail approx. a week later.</p>
<p><strong>Update:</strong> NemID is replaced by a new system called MitID. Many online services now exclusively offer the authentication via MitID. I have no information about the first-time registration for MitID, as I converted my previous NemID to a MitID</p>
<h3 id="nemid">NemID</h3>
<p>NB: NemID is now (almost) fully deprecated. The new system is called MitID, but the idea stays the same.</p>
<p>I have seen many different explanations of the NemID, which all seemed a bit abstract to me, so I
will try to explain it myself as simple as possible. In order to log in to government or other
official online services, an authentication is used which is called NemID. It is tightly coupled to
the CPR number and involves a 2-Factor-Authentification with your phone or a physical code card
(I would highly recommend the app, though).</p>
<h3 id="bank-account">Bank Account</h3>
<p>Before you can open a Danish bank account, an account with a cheap conversion of currencies saves
you a lot of conversion fees. For that, I use Revolut (so do many other fellow students), which
makes it easy and cheap to transfer money (e.g. in EUR) and swap it to DKK (with a maximum of
0.5% fee after a certain transfer volume).</p>
<p>If you want to receive government support like SU or Boligstøtte, however, a Danish bank account facilitates the procress immensely. After hearing about long queues and waiting times for banks like
Danske Bank, widely used by many students, I tried the Danish online bank Lunar, which lets
you open an account online without any waiting time. The approval process needed approximately one week,
and afterwards you are set to go. The Danish government transfers money (e.g. government support, tax refunds etc.) to your so-called NemKonto,
which can be seen as the government-known account. You can request your account at Lunar to be your
NemKonto directly from the app.</p>
<h3 id="digital-post">Digital Post</h3>
<p>Another fully digitalised system is the so-called Digital Post, which almost completely replaces the physical letter correspondence with the authorities. It is a special E-Mail inbox, which is used to
communicate with different institutions in the Danish administrative. There is an app (called Digital Post) you can use, otherwise you find your inbox on all of the following websites:</p>
<ul>
<li>borger.dk</li>
<li>e-Boks.dk</li>
<li>mit.dk</li>
</ul>
<p>NB: You can see mail from authorities on all of the websites. However, certain banks or companies can
have agreements with only one of those providers, making their mails only visible in the corresponding provider&rsquo;s inbox. One example could be payslips, which could be issued by a company e.g. only in e-Boks. Therefore, it can be beneficial to check all of the providers regularly.</p>
<h3 id="mobilepay">MobilePay</h3>
<p>MobilePay is a money transfer app, similar to PayPal, just for Danish citizens. After downloading the app, you can register with your NemID / MitID, a Danish phone number and Danish bank account. Afterwards, you can send and request money to / from your contacts or any Danish number. Sometimes, you can pay in shops (or e.g. the flea market) via MobilePay as well.</p>
<h3 id="tax-card">Tax Card</h3>
<p>For the tax card, it can be said that it can be requested online as well. The term &ldquo;tax card&rdquo; can be seen as a synonym for &ldquo;tax registration&rdquo;, meaning that you receive a personal tax number and have access to the central tax administration system at skat.dk.</p>
<p>When the Danish Tax Agency creates a personal tax number, your employer will receive your tax number automatically. There are two accounts coupled to the tax card, the A card (hovedkort) and B card (bikort). The A card has a certain allowance per tax year, while on the B card, you are fully taxed on all income. If you have two sources of income (e.g. SU and a student job), one of the sources <strong>has</strong> to be directed to the B card, otherwise it can occur that too much allowance is granted, resulting in a back payment of unpaid taxes.</p>
<p>The recommendation from government is that SU stays on the A card, while your student income is directed on the B card. For that, a notification to your employer is sufficient indicating that you would like to use the B card.</p>
<h3 id="public-transport">Public Transport</h3>
<p>The public transport in and around Copenhagen is very extensive and easily usable. The easiest first option is a so-called Anonymous Rejsekort (travel card). You can buy them at Rejsekort retailers, which are often shops/kiosks at train stations. The card is not bound to a person and can be shared with others (even multiple people at the same time). Also, you can save compared to regular tickets when travelling outside rush hours. The card is great to lend to friends who are visiting and don&rsquo;t want to buy single tickets all day. With all Rejsekorts, you can clock in and out on the blue buttons at train stations / in busses. It is <strong>very important</strong> to clock out after a ride, otherwise a fine will be issued.</p>
<p>Two other options that I want to mention are the Personal Rejsekort and the Ungdomskort. The Personal Rejsekort offers similar services as the anonymous one, but allows to top up online (also automatically when below a certain threshold), see recent trips etc. It is, however, bound to a person and cannot be transferred. Check whether the &ldquo;Young&rdquo; option applies to you as a traveler type to get a discounted price.</p>
<p>The Ungdomskort (youth card) is like a flat rate for public transport. You can travel without topping up, clocking in and out etc. at a fixed pre-paid rate. For that, you either receive a physical card or a digital one on your phone. Also, you have to be a student (in higher education) to be able to request the Ungdomskort. Contact the university at <a href="mailto:ungdomskort@adm.ku.dk">ungdomskort@adm.ku.dk</a> to confirm that you&rsquo;re enrolled. NB: The Ungdomskort is pre-paid in so-called periods (default is 30 days). If you choose a physical card, you&rsquo;ll receive a new one for each period (meaning each month, which can be annoying). Therefore, make sure to choose longer periods if you want to receive fewer physical cards.</p>
<h3 id="boligstøtte">Boligstøtte</h3>
<p>Boligstøtte (Housing support) is what the name suggests. It can be requested per kitchen (so if you have a kitchenette in your dorm, you can still apply) and means a monthly budget issued by the government to help you pay your rent. For me, it is around 12% of my monthly rent.</p>
<h2 id="working--su">Working &amp; SU</h2>
<p>The last section shall be dedicated to SU (Statens Uddannelsesstøtte), which is a government-funded support for students. Intended mainly for Danish students, the option for EU students is the so-called &ldquo;equal status&rdquo;, which can be achieved by working for a Danish company. Then, you&rsquo;ll receive the government support alongside your student job income, which really adds up! In 2021, SU amounted to DKK 6.321 per month before taxes (around 850€). The only real condition bound to receiving SU as a worker is to work 10-12 hours per week, continously each week. Especially in the first weeks, make sure to log those hours each week. After some time (10 weeks for me), there are options to request SU holiday, meaning that it is possible to take a week off in which the government does not check the logged hours.</p>
<p>Speaking of holiday, make sure to get your feriepenge (holiday allowance). Your employer pays a certain amount each month to a separate account, which can be disbursed when going on vacation.</p>
<h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2>
<p>I hope this guide gave you some insights into the different processes and services when studying in Copenhagen! As said in the beginning, a guide like this would have helped me with a few hints and things to look out for when navigating the administrative landscape.</p>
]]></content></item><item><title>Hello World</title><link>https://www.hauptvogel.dev/posts/hello-world/</link><pubDate>Wed, 24 Aug 2022 22:20:11 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://www.hauptvogel.dev/posts/hello-world/</guid><description>Hej! Jeg hedder Nick og jeg er 23 år gammel. Jeg er fra Tyskland og skal studere datalogi på Københavns Universitet fra september 2022. Jeg er flyttet til København for et par dage siden, men jeg har lært dansk i et par måneder. Med indlæg som disse vil jeg gerne dokumentere mine fremskridt med at lære sproget.
More than that, I want to utilize this blog to keep track of my studies&amp;rsquo; progress.</description><content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="/static/copenhagen_helloworld.jpg" alt="Hello Copenhagen!"></p>
<p>Hej! Jeg hedder Nick og jeg er 23 år gammel. Jeg er fra Tyskland og skal studere datalogi på Københavns Universitet fra september 2022.
Jeg er flyttet til København for et par dage siden, men jeg har lært dansk i et par måneder. Med indlæg som disse vil jeg gerne dokumentere mine fremskridt med at lære sproget.</p>
<p>More than that, I want to utilize this blog to keep track of my studies&rsquo; progress. From time to time, I will compose short articles, either about the Danish language, a particularly interesting topic from my M.Sc. studies or just a random thought that came to my mind while biking to the university. &#x1f6b2;</p>
<p>Welcome to my blog and stay tuned! &#x1f4d6;</p>
]]></content></item></channel></rss>