<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>copenhagen on Nick Hauptvogel</title><link>https://www.hauptvogel.dev/tags/copenhagen/</link><description>Recent content in copenhagen on Nick Hauptvogel</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><copyright>&lt;a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">CC BY-NC 4.0&lt;/a></copyright><lastBuildDate>Sat, 19 Nov 2022 15:20:11 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://www.hauptvogel.dev/tags/copenhagen/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Copenhagen Student 101 - A guide to studying and surviving as a foreign student in Copenhagen, Denmark</title><link>https://www.hauptvogel.dev/posts/study_survive_in_copenhagen_guide/</link><pubDate>Sat, 19 Nov 2022 15:20:11 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://www.hauptvogel.dev/posts/study_survive_in_copenhagen_guide/</guid><description>Introduction In August 2022, I moved from my hometown Bremen in Germany to Copenhangen, Denmark, in order to start my Master&amp;rsquo;s Degree studies in Computer Science at the University of Copenhagen. After finishing my B.Sc. Degree in Computer Engineering in 2021, the strive for international experience and an continuation in the academic research environment led me to the decision to perform my Master&amp;rsquo;s degree abroad.
Early on, I started with the preparation of my stay abroad and gathered information about administrative tasks, but also student life advices.</description></item><item><title>Hello World</title><link>https://www.hauptvogel.dev/posts/hello-world/</link><pubDate>Wed, 24 Aug 2022 22:20:11 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://www.hauptvogel.dev/posts/hello-world/</guid><description>Hej! Jeg hedder Nick og jeg er 23 år gammel. Jeg er fra Tyskland og skal studere datalogi på Københavns Universitet fra september 2022. Jeg er flyttet til København for et par dage siden, men jeg har lært dansk i et par måneder. Med indlæg som disse vil jeg gerne dokumentere mine fremskridt med at lære sproget.
More than that, I want to utilize this blog to keep track of my studies&amp;rsquo; progress.</description></item></channel></rss>